December. The winter solstice has passed,
and our school was in winter vacation.
12 月　冬至も越え
私たちの学校は　冬休みを迎えていた
With the pairing of the leg shield,
which was originally installed,
私のカブは　もともとついていたレッグシールドと
and the new windshield that I had put on,
新しく取り付けたウインドシールドの組み合わせで
the problem of cold on my Cub
had been largely solved.
寒さという問題は　大幅に改善されていた
カッコ悪いから嫌だと言っていた礼子も
Reiko had resisted at first,
saying that they didn't look cool,
but eventually gave in to the cold
and installed leg shields.
結局寒さに負けて　レッグシールドをつけた
The matter of the cold had been settled,
and we could now ride our Cubs freely.
寒さ対策も一段落
これで自由にカブで走り回れる
Any time we wanted, wherever
we wanted, just as we had before.
今までどおりいつでも　どこまでも
Koguma-san!
小熊さん！
買い物？
Going shopping?
Yes, up to Nirasaki to buy
some coffee beans.
はい　韮崎までコーヒー豆を買いに
気をつけて
Be careful.
Right!
はい！
彼女はお店のイートイン・スペースを
She had been moving
forward with her project
to turn her shop's eat-in space
into an Italian bar.
イタリアンバールに改造する計画を進めていた
Apparently, she was working
at the post office,
郵便局でバイトをして
and had been scouring the town
for things she could use in her bar.
街までバールで使えそうな物を探しにいっているらしい
寒っ…
Brr...
That day, spread out before my gaze...
その日　私の目の前には
カブに乗り始めて初めての
...for the first time since
I started riding my Cub...
銀世界が広がっていた
...was a whole world of silver.
初めての小さな旅路
目的地ならいらないよ
何もない私の頬に
手招きするように風が吹く
寄り道　回り道
いつもの景色も鮮やかに
右手をひねるたび　何度でも胸が弾むから
さあ　ギアを上げて　顔を上げて
どこまでも伸びてく道だって
昨日より少し遠くまで
きみとなら怖くない　どこだって
私ひとりでは　作れない風だ
I can't ride in this.
これじゃ乗れないか…
"Reiko"
--Hello--
--Come on over, now!
もしもし…
すぐに来て！
--No way.
--Just come over!
嫌だ
いいから　来て！
I've got something here
that's a ton of fun!
すっごくおもしろいものがあるから！
"Look at this!!"
"Open attached image"
Hello.
もしもし？
I'll be right over.
今から行く
Welcome.
いらっしゃい
Is that it?
それ？
Yep. Tire chains for a Super Cub.
そっ　スーパーカブ用のタイヤチェーン
Where did you come by
something like those?
そんなもの　どこで手に入れたの？
I heard that the newspaper distributor
in Sagamihara was going out of business,
相模原の新聞販売店が廃業するって聞いてね
so I went to see if maybe I could
score some parts for our Cubs,
カブのパーツでも手に入らないかと思って　行ってみたけど
ひと足遅かったわ
but I was a little too late.
The chassis and parts
had all been taken away,
車体やパーツは持っていかれてて
and all that was left was this
dead weight that nobody bid on.
残ったのはこんな重いのに値がつかないものだけ
Hmm...
At least I thought it was, but I wasn't
expecting it to come in handy so soon.
な～んて思ってたけど
まさかこんなすぐ役に立つことになるとはね
You want to put yours on, too?
アンタもつけてみる？
Yes!
つける！
"Check the configuration
of your tire chains!"
"Before putting them on,
understand their design."
うん
Mm-hmm.
Where are we going?
どこへ行く？
もっと上に行くと　おもしろい所があるわよ
If we head on up higher,
there's the coolest place.
上？
Up?
Here we go!
いくよ！
Yahoo!
"Super Cub"
"Episode 10"
"Snow"
Woo-hoo!
チェーン代ってわけね
In exchange for the chains,
right? All of it?
全部？
バカ　半分だけ
Just half, dummy.
It's still a little bit warm.
まだちょっとあったかい
Here.
はい
Thanks.
ありがとう
いくよ～！
Here goes!
Whoo!
Not good enough!
甘い！
Come on, come on!
ほらほら！
このぉ…
Why, you...!
Whoa! Using your Cub is foul play!
ちょ… カブ使うのは反則でしょ！
You're the one who started it!
先に仕掛けたのはそっち！
All right, all right, I give up!
わかった　わかった　降参！
Easy! I said I give up!
ちょっと！降参だってば！
This feels so good!
気持ちいい！
ねぇ　楽しい？
Hey, having fun?
うん　楽しい
Mm-hmm, I am.
冬って楽しいわね
Winter is fun, huh?
Mm-hmm.
うん
When you have a Cub, winter is fun.
カブがあれば　冬は楽しい
行こっか
Ready to go?
うん…
Mm-hmm.
Ah, Reiko-chan, Koguma-san!
礼子ちゃん　小熊さん！
Ahem... This way, please.
さぁ　こちらへどうぞ
All right.
はいは～い
Huh?
あれ？
Hmm? What's the matter?
どうしたの？
Something seems different from usual.
何かいつもと違うような…
It's the tablecloth and chairs.
テーブルクロスとイスが
トリコローレカラーね
The Tricolore flag colors.
It looks like Italy is steadily
enlarging its territory.
イタリアは順調に領土を広げてるってわけだ
Yes.
はい！
もう～誘ってくれればよかったのに～
Aw, I wish you would have
invited me to come, too.
自転車じゃ無理だって
You couldn't have made it on a bicycle.
モールトンならたぶん大丈夫です
I probably would have been
fine on my Moulton.
今度私も行こうかな
Maybe I'll go up there sometime.
I'll come with you when you do.
そのときは一緒に行く
次は椎ちゃんを乗せて甲斐駒の山を走り降りてあげるわよ
Next time, I'll let you ride with me,
and we'll go up and down Mt. Kaikoma.
I have the perfect "seat" for you, too.
ちょうどいい専用席もあるしね
"Seat"?
専用席？
あ～れ
In there.
ちょっと　椎ちゃん！冗談よ
Whoa, Shii-chan, I'm joking.
礼子ちゃんのその笑顔は信用できない
Reiko-chan, I don't trust that smile.
She might fit in the front
basket of my Cub, too.
私のカブの前カゴにも入るかも
え～っ　小熊さんまで!?
Huh?! Not you, too, Koguma-san!
Hey, welcome!
やぁ　いらっしゃい
小熊さん
Koguma-san...
今日はグァテマラのフレンチローストでいいかな？
Will Guatemalan French
Roast be okay today?
I'll leave it to you.
お任せします
Hello.
こんちは～
お待たせ～
Thanks for waiting!
林道は雪と凍結で　車両はもう通行できないって
Between the snow and icing,
they say the forest roads
are impassible to vehicles.
今あそこを使ってるのは　シカやイノシシだけ
The only ones using them right now
are the deer and wild boar.
シカもイノシシも　もう使ってないかも
The deer and wild boar may not
even be using them anymore.
We don't get too much accumulation
around here, but with the wind...
この辺はそんなに積もらないけど　風だけはね…
Yeah. But for what these cost,
they're worth it.
そうねぇ
でも　それなりの値段しただけはある
ワークブーツもね
Same for these work boots.
うん
Mm-hmm.
ウインドシールドとレッグシールドもあるし
We have our windshields
and leg shields now,
何時間走っても寒くなくなった
and we can ride for hours
without getting cold.
新調したヘルメットのシールドもいい感じ
The upgraded shield for
my helmet is also nice.
気温が下がっても　それに合わせた装備を加えれば
Even when the temperature drops,
if we add on the right gear,
対処できるってことね
it's nothing we can't deal with.
お待ちどおさま
Thank you for waiting.
どうぞ
Here you go.
Thank you very much.
ありがとうございます
Thanks for the coffee.
いただきます
Where's Shii-chan today?
今日椎ちゃんは？
Sorry about that, and after you
came all the way over, too.
すみませんね
せっかく来てもらったのに　ちょっと出かけてて
She went out for a bit.
あぁ　イタリア化計画か
Ah, the Italian project.
She likely went into town
to look at a bunch of stuff.
街までいろいろ見にいってるみたいで
ネコ道に入っていくのを見ました
I saw her turning onto the cat trail.
ネコ道？
Cat trail?
県道から七里岩ラインに抜ける…
The one that cuts from the prefectural
road through to the Shichiriiwa Line.
Oh, that narrow little road.
あぁ　あの細い道
It's quicker to get to the train
station that way on a bicycle.
自転車なら　あっちのほうが駅まで近いから
イタリア… どこまで広がるかな
I wonder how far Italy
is going to spread now.
Koguma-san and Reiko-san, it looks like
you two have been an influence on her.
小熊さんと礼子さんに影響を受けてるみたいでね
Hmm?
お二人に憧れてるんですよ
She wants to be like the two of you.
私たちに？
Like us?
えぇ
Yes. She seems to be riding
her bicycle around a lot more,
買い物以外にもよく自転車に乗って　いろいろ回ってるみたいで
even when she's not shopping.
まるで　お二人のあとを追いかけてるみたいに
Almost as if she's trying
to catch up to you two.
私に押しつけられて乗っていたアレックス・モールトンですが
I'm the one who pushed the
Alex Moulton she's riding on her,
やっと好きになってくれたようで
and now that she finally seems
to have taken a liking to it,
I kind of feel happy about it.
なんだか　うれしいです
コメリに寄ってくけど　アンタは？
I'm going to stop by Komeri.
How about you?
今日はいい
Not today.
Okay.
そっ
It looks like another cold one tomorrow.
明日も寒くなりそう
Just because we're adding
gear to keep out the cold,
装備を増やして　寒くなくなっても
it doesn't mean things
are getting any warmer.
それは暖かくなるってことではないからね
私たちは気づいていた
We had come to realize something...
The real reason why bikers call
winter both a foe and a trial.
冬がバイク乗りにとって
敵とも試練とも言われる　本当の理由
And that... was not because of the cold,
but because of how long it lasts.
それは　寒さではなく
その長さにあるのだと
In another few months, spring would
once again come to the Southern Alps,
あと数か月もすれば
この南アルプスの地にも春が訪れ　桜が咲く
and the cherry blossoms would bloom.
けれど
However, for those of us on our Cubs,
spring is still out of reach,
カブに乗る私たちにとって
春はまだ　手を伸ばしても届かず
目を凝らしても見えないほど遠かった
and too far away to see,
even by squinting.
"Eniwa Shii"
もしもし？
Hello?
たす… けて
...lp... me...
Huh?
えっ
Help me...
助けて！
Help... me...
たす… けて…
すれ違う風　未来に溶けてく
近づいてくる　優しいエンジンの音
透明だった世界に　車輪で色を付けよう
ともに駆け抜けた道
誰にも描けない私の絵になる
遠くで春が呼ぶ　すぐそこかもしれない
できるだけたくさんの　思い出連れてこう
一緒に過ごす日々　見つけた彩りは決して
色褪せない
いつだってずっと　そばにいるよ
"A Distant Spring"
"Super Cub Episode 11"
Episode 11: "A Distant Spring."
第 11 話　「遠い春」